<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Jeff Skelton</title>
    <description>Software Developer
</description>
    <link>https://www.jeffskelton.net/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://www.jeffskelton.net/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Mon, 15 May 2017 22:40:55 -0700</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 15 May 2017 22:40:55 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.4.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Be Clear, Not Clever</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Write code that is easy to delete, not easy to extend.” - &lt;a href=&quot;http://programmingisterrible.com/post/139222674273/write-code-that-is-easy-to-delete-not-easy-to&quot;&gt;Programming Is Terrible&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most common pitfalls I see in beginner to intermediate level programmers is a desire to optimize their code for extensibility too early in the process. While this sounds like a good idea, often they try to solve for problems that are not explicitly stated in the requirements. In other words, they try to write code that can adapt to &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; changes and not just the ones they know about. This is a mistake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Premature optimization is the root of all evil” - &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikiquote.org/wiki/Donald_Knuth&quot;&gt;Donald Knuth&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A more experienced developer follows the philosophy of &lt;strong&gt;make it work, make it good, make it fast&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-make-it-work&quot;&gt;1) Make it work&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, do whatever needs to be done to make the feature work. Write tests which state the expected behavior and verify that they fail. Begin writing your code. Ignore code quality to a reasonable extent and duplication is ok for the time being. The only focus here is getting tests to pass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-make-it-good&quot;&gt;2) Make it good&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The process of building out a new feature exposes the areas that need to be optimized. This is the time to review what has been built and begin refactoring. Duplication should be eliminated. Variables and function names should be carefully thought out. Code should be modularized and organized into logical sections. All tests should continue to pass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-make-it-fast&quot;&gt;3) Make it fast&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Identify any obvious performance bottlenecks. Revisit this step as the new feature is used. The areas for optimization will become obvious. As stated before, avoid making assumptions or writing overly torturous logic to solve for problems you don’t yet have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;common-trouble-spots&quot;&gt;Common trouble spots&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“You wanted a banana but what you got was a gorilla holding the banana and the entire jungle.” - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1430219483?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=theende-20&amp;amp;linkCode=xm2&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creativeASIN=1430219483&quot;&gt;Joe Armstrong, creator of Erlang&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not a purist. I believe that whatever gets the job done with the least amount of complexity, is the right approach. It’s trendy today to bash on Object Oriented Programming (OOP) but I feel that to be overly dogmatic. OOP has a lot of powerful comcepts and an inexperienced programmer can easily abuse them by trying do too much too early.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;abuse-of-inheritance&quot;&gt;Abuse of inheritance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my opinion abuse of inheritance is the biggest culprit. Inheritance, when done right can be a powerful concept. When done wrong it can create a massive headache as a codebase increases in size and complexity. In Steve McConnel’s excellent book &lt;a href=&quot;/2017/03/12/recommended-reading.html&quot;&gt;Code Complete 2&lt;/a&gt;, he recommends limiting levels of inheritance to no more than 3 levels. I would argue that that number should be 2 unless there is a very good reason. More importantly I feel that using inheritance can wait until much later in the process when its much more clear where it will be useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/QM1iUe6IofM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;*I don’t agree that OOP is bad. However, I do think that the author brings up some good points.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Functional programming teaches us some valuable techniques. It teaches us to write our code as a series of small, composable blocks. We chain these blocks together and build complex pipelines of logic. Each block has a single responsibility. This approach allows us to easily delete or change that block of logic with minimal danger of affecting the entire application. A good deal of the time I find this to be the best way to approach things. &lt;strong&gt;Whenever possible, write code that is explicit in its dependencies.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of the reasons I love working with a language like Elixir. It allows for elegant code blocks like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot; data-lang=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;    
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;doTheThing&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;|&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;doTheNextThing&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;|&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;doTheFinalThing&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In JavaScript we can accomplish something similar with promise chaining:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-javascript&quot; data-lang=&quot;javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;doTheThing&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;then&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;doTheNextThing&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;then&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;doTheFinalThing&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is powerful because if I wanted to add a new piece of logic to my code, I can simply add it to the chain:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-javascript&quot; data-lang=&quot;javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;doTheThing&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;then&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;doTheNextThing&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;then&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;doAThirdThing&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;then&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;doTheFinalThing&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;abuse-of-novel-languageframework-features&quot;&gt;Abuse of novel language/framework features&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This doesn’t just affect traditional code either. Take this Sass example I just saw at a frontend conference recently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-javascript&quot; data-lang=&quot;javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;primary&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;rail&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;@&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;extend&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;pull&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;left&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;col&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;md&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;6&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;small&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The speaker presents this as a clever way to encapsulate all his CSS classes into one large “God” class. While it’s neat that you &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; do this. It’s a terrible idea in practice. What happens for example if he encounters a case where the column needs to be a different size? He can’t change it here without affecting everything else. What about cases where he only wants some but not all of those classes? Whats worse, he has abstracted away some relatively well known bootstrap classes in favor of his own domain specific language (DSL). Now any new developer that works on his code needs to root about to find out what that class does. As the application ages, it will become increasingly unclear what the ramifications of changing that class would mean to the application at large. Since that styling likely touches a lot of areas in the application, no one will dare change it for fear that it will have largely unforseen consequences. It is for this reason that I strongly recommend a more modular approach. The time saved by encapsulating these classes behind a DSL is lost in the mental overhead required to understand it and the long term maintenance overhead it presents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a fact that the code we write today will come back to haunt us later. With every line comes a cost. It’s best to avoid writing any more than necessary. Code that doesn’t exist cannot break and cannot hurt us. When writing it, be clear, be concise, and avoid being clever.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 21 Mar 2017 11:24:47 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.jeffskelton.net/2017/03/21/be-clear-not-clever.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.jeffskelton.net/2017/03/21/be-clear-not-clever.html</guid>
        
        <category>programming</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Recommended Reading</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Last update: March 2017&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A curated list of books that I have found to be useful in my career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-pragmatic-programmer&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Pragmatic-Programmer-Journeyman-Master/dp/020161622X&quot;&gt;The Pragmatic Programmer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Pragmatic-Programmer-Journeyman-Master/dp/020161622X&quot; class=&quot;image-post-link&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/recommended-reading/pragmatic-programmer-cover.jpg&quot; class=&quot;image-post&quot; alt=&quot;The Pragmatic Programmer&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
My all time favorite computer science book. If I had to choose just one, this would be it. I keep my copy on my desk at my office and often pick it up, flip to a random chapter, and start reading. No matter how many times I have done this, I find something new. There have been times where I have been stuck on a tricky problem and used it to shake my thinking up à la &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oblique_Strategies&quot;&gt;Oblique Strategies&lt;/a&gt;. I love that it covers high level concepts and avoids language specific topics. The authors talk about programming as a craft and clearly love their subject.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;code-complete-2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/dp/0735619670/&quot;&gt;Code Complete 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/dp/0735619670/&quot; class=&quot;image-post-link&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/recommended-reading/code-complete-2.jpg&quot; class=&quot;image-post&quot; alt=&quot;Code Complete 2&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
Jeff Atwood likes this book so much that he named his &lt;a href=&quot;https://codinghorror.com&quot;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt; after it. No other book covers the craft of programming so completely. It’s a thick volume and not one that is easy to read cover to cover. However, the concepts it teaches are timeless so it’s worth doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;javascript-the-good-parts&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/JavaScript-Good-Parts-Douglas-Crockford/dp/0596517742&quot;&gt;JavaScript: The Good Parts&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/JavaScript-Good-Parts-Douglas-Crockford/dp/0596517742&quot; class=&quot;image-post-link&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/recommended-reading/javascript-the-good-parts.jpg&quot; class=&quot;image-post&quot; alt=&quot;JavaScript: The Good Parts&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
JavaScript is, well, &lt;em&gt;weird&lt;/em&gt;. It’s hugely expressive and powerful but only to those that know which features to use and which to avoid. Understanding hoisting or type inference for instance can be mind bending to the uninitiated. ES6 has done a lot to cover up the more troublesome parts of JavaScript but it’s good to be aware of the pitfalls. The author, Douglas Crockford invented the language so this is as good as it gets in explaining it. This book is small and just dense with knowledge. The terse style at times make it a challenging read. I’ve yet to find a better resource for helping navigate all the language’s quirks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;programming-phoenix&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Programming-Phoenix-Productive-Reliable-Fast/dp/1680501453/&quot;&gt;Programming Phoenix&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Programming-Phoenix-Productive-Reliable-Fast/dp/1680501453/&quot; class=&quot;image-post-link&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/recommended-reading/programming-phoenix.jpg&quot; class=&quot;image-post&quot; alt=&quot;Programming Phoenix&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, this one is not for everyone. Only developers interested in working with Elixir and the Phoenix framework should read. I included it because it’s simply the best written technical guide I’ve ever used. The authors provide a real world application to build that teaches the essential concepts of the Phoenix framework. They dumb nothing down. By the time I finished this book I felt I could fully grasp this technology and was able to directly apply it to several client projects I was working on. I rarely find this to be the case with most books of this stripe. I am rooting for Elixir to succeed and become widely adopted. If it does it will be because of efforts like this book that make it easy to onboard new developers.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 12 Mar 2017 22:42:33 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.jeffskelton.net/2017/03/12/recommended-reading.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.jeffskelton.net/2017/03/12/recommended-reading.html</guid>
        
        <category>programming</category>
        
        <category>books</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Hello World</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I love being a software developer. It’s a creative, challenging, and fun profession. When done well, it’s an art form in the same way a beautiful building or finely crafted piece of furniture can be. To a creative, slightly nerdy guy like me, its a great fit. I feel fortunate to have stumbled into it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thats not to say it’s all good times. It’s not “fun” to be debugging a broken deployment at three in the morning or tracking down some tricky logic bug. Its not “challenging” or “creative” to be writing up documentation or sitting in a meeting. However, in between those moments of drudgery, I get to solve problems. That “aha!” moment when I solve a particularly tough one is hard to beat. My brain becomes flooded with dopamine and for a moment I am convinced of my divinity. That is until I notice that my solution has a few flaws. I come crashing back down to earth and get back to work. Problems are the job and I try to remember that. If it was easy, everyone would do it. It’s not and therefore I have a career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the years I’ve watched things change tremendously. Frameworks come and go, techniques and languages that were once darlings of the industry have been now cast aside as outdated and terrible. If you would have told me when I started that &lt;em&gt;JavaScript&lt;/em&gt; would be the dominant programming language of 2017 I would have wondered what you were smoking. Yet it is, and I can tell you with absolute certainty that this too shall one day pass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No matter how good I get or how much I know, there will always be a new technique or technology out there. At times that can be a bit exhausting and it’s a fact that my &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.admarco.net/inbound-marketing-messaging-sales-performance-blog/bid/113040/The-Half-Life-of-a-Learned-Skill-is-5-years-Toward-a-New-Culture-of-Learning&quot;&gt;skills have a half life&lt;/a&gt;. With that in mind, it becomes obvious that only those with an enthusiasm for learning will continue to find work. It’s not what I know right now, its how I find the information I need to solve what I don’t. I’m thankful to all the developers that take the time to write down how they solve a challenge. When I need help with a similar one, it will be there. By documenting our successes we all are elevated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its in that spirit that I have decided to join the club. I have challenged myself to write one post a week. That is a sustainable pace in my opinion. I plan to start by writing about technical challenges that I encounter and how I overcome them. I will also be writing tutorials and documentation on subjects that I feel aren’t adequately covered by whats currently out there in the world. Along the way I hope to discover my own voice and perhaps begin to inject some of that into my writing. Wish me luck.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 07 Mar 2017 21:57:15 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.jeffskelton.net/2017/03/07/hello-world.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.jeffskelton.net/2017/03/07/hello-world.html</guid>
        
        <category>programming</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
